All
Speaker 1: right. Thanks, everyone, for joining this press conference this morning. This call is being recorded and will be distributed widely after it wraps. In just a second, I'll hand things over to Senator Murray. After each of our three speakers
on the
Speaker 1: call have given their remarks, we'll have time for questions from any members of the media in attendance. And during Q&A, we'll ask folks to use the raise hand function and say their name and outline. So with all of that, I'm going
to go
Speaker 1: ahead and turn things over to
Senator Murray.
All right,
Speaker 2: well, thank you all for joining
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): me here today. We are here to put a spotlight on an issue Republicans are trying as hard as they possibly can to ignore: the health care crisis they have created, which is forcing people to lose their health insurance, hospitals to close their doors, and will soon mean millions of Americans will pay more than double what they pay now for their health care premiums if Congress does not
act.
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): Seriously,
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): Republicans have decided they would rather shut down the government than talk to Democrats
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): about preventing premiums from exploding next year. One big issue with that Republican plan, ignoring or lying about it, this problem is not going to go away. Families with health care at stake know this all too well because when you
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): go online to buy health insurance and find your monthly payment has more than doubled, you're going to notice it.
When
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): your health care is suddenly way out of budget for your family, that's not something you will ignore. In fact, it is something that will break the bank for many people and force millions to simply drop their coverage altogether. I
don't know
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): why Republicans think they can just sweep this health care crisis they created under the rug.
But
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): we are here to say we are forcing this issue. We are going to talk about health care, whether Republicans want to or not. And it's clear as day they do not, because they know their position is unpopular. A top House Republican recently said as much in private and urged colleagues, don't talk about it. So Democrats are going to force Republicans to come to the table to negotiate with us.
The
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): American people are demanding action, and they are demanding it now. Why? Because the new higher health care rates, those are being set right now. Notifications to families, they're in the mail now. Open enrollment is weeks away, and families are panicking. I have heard from one family in my home state of Washington whose premiums could jump from $278 a month to as much as $1,800 a month.
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): There is a simple solution here, to simply save the ACA tax credits that 22 million people rely on to afford health care, including over 200,000 people in Washington state. But Republicans have made clear they would quite literally shut down the government rather than address this problem. What
do they
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): plan on telling farmers that a quarter of them are enrolled in the health care exchanges?
Yes.
They
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): will see their costs increase exponentially. What do they plan to tell small business owners and workers and people who are self-employed, half of whom get their coverage through the ACA exchanges? Because saying tough
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): luck is not going to cut it, and neither is we'll fix it later, for that matter. Later is too late.
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): Republicans are saying they will just sit on their hands until those higher rates are locked in for the next year, and that is unacceptable.
We
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): have to act now. Families know it. Patients know it. Small business owners know it. And that's why Democrats are insisting on acting now. We are not going to let Republicans keep sabotaging Americans' health
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): care. Democrats are fighting to reverse the cuts, lower costs, and protect health care for the people we represent
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): back home.
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): People who are speaking out about just how devastating it will be if Republicans refuse to save these critical
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): health care tax credits. I
am joined
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): by some of them today. Republicans may shut down the government, but they're not going to shut down this debate. And they will not shut out the voices of people across the country who
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): want us to act before their health care costs skyrocket, before their insurance is out of reach,
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): before it is too late.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): So with that, let me turn it over and thank Commissioner Patty Kuderer for joining me today.
Thank you, Senator Marie,
Speaker 7: for your leadership and for pulling us all together here today.
So my office
Speaker 7: oversees the individual health insurance market.
This is the
Speaker 7: market where people buy coverage if they don't have employer-sponsored coverage. And it's also where many people who are self-employed and early retirees get coverage.
I'm
Speaker 7: proud of the work that Washington State did to implement the Affordable Care Act. Because of this effort, we enjoy a robust, competitive individual market and a historically low uninsured rate of 4.8%.
We achieved
Speaker 7: this success because we embraced Medicaid expansion and because we helped people buy coverage through premium tax credits.
Speaker 7: Last year, more than 216,000 people in the individual market qualified for enhanced premium tax credits.
Simply put, tax
Speaker 7: credits are crucial for helping people afford and keep coverage. This year, insurers requested a 21.2% rate increase. We found that 21% was justified, and state law requires us to approve that rate change if they can justify their request.
Up to
Speaker 7: 7% of that increase, however, is due to the expiration of the enhanced premium tax credits. And I want to be clear, that's just the base rate increase, not the net increase that people will see. And
I want to be
Speaker 7: also very clear that people are going to find it very hard to absorb these increases without financial help. Our exchange predicts that 80,000 people will drop coverage if enhanced premium tax credits are not extended.
If
Speaker 7: fewer people are enrolled because of cost, older and sicker people will remain, dropping up costs for everyone.
And this,
Speaker 7: along with the growing uncertainty at the federal level, does not bode well for the next year.
And as
Speaker 7: your insurance commissioner, I can tell you what insurers do not like, and that's uncertainty. Uncertainty does not create a stable, vibrant, competitive market. It creates chaos and high costs for consumers.
It's
Speaker 7: time for Republicans to stop playing politics with people's health care and make these premium tax credits permanent. And now you'll hear from Maya Tusing, a Washington small business owner who relies on the ACA tax credits to afford health care.
Speaker 8: Maya.
Thank you,
Speaker 9: Commissioner Kuderer. And thank you, Senator Patty Murray, for giving me this platform. Her commitment to highlighting health care stories of Americans is very important.
My
Speaker 9: name is Maya Tusing. I live in Woodinville, Washington, with my husband and teenage daughter and grew up on the east side of King County.
And six
Speaker 9: years ago, I launched a small business with a partner that helps nonprofits manage their
Speaker 10: financial resources. We're lean, we're mission-driven, and we're growing.
And
Speaker 10: most importantly, we are passionate about what we do. However, we're not large enough to provide me and my family with employer-sponsored health insurance. And that's why the ACA was a lifeline for me, because it allowed us to focus on building our business without my agonizing over how to secure health insurance.
Speaker 10: And at the time, it seemed like a stroke of luck and an example of the U.S.'s brilliant policy innovation. And it sounds a bit sappy, but it was the first time I really felt fortunate to be an American because of the incredible dynamism in this country and the fact that everyone here is so supportive of small business owners and it seems so easy to launch a business.
But
Speaker 10: while our take-home pay grew steadily, our health care premium spiked, and last year they increased five-fold, and with the expiration of tax credits, they'll double, making it tenfold, a tenfold increase in two years. And our health care costs could cost more than our home, life, and auto insurance combined.
Okay.
So
Speaker 10: running a small business requires reliable expense forecasting, and that means that if these credits expire, many entrepreneurs will face sudden premium spikes that they couldn't have anticipated. And that kind of unpredictability can be devastating, especially when it's driven by policy decisions that are totally beyond our control.
Speaker 10: Now, I'm more fortunate than most Americans in that I have an MBA from the University of Washington that allowed me good-paying jobs, that allowed me to own a home, I fully funded my retirement, I saved enough to bootstrap the small business that I run today, but I was totally unprepared to squeeze an additional $1,000 a month just to keep my existing health plan.
And
Speaker 10: while some Americans may lapse coverage, I cannot. I have a family I care about and a business partner and two employees who count on me to show up to the office every day. And if things get desperate, I could tap my IRA, but I'd pay penalties regularly.
Speaker 10: because I'm far from retirement age and taxes just to afford the premiums and that's not sustainable or fair for that matter. And after that, my family would have to scrutinize every dollar toward care, so for example, does my back hurt enough to go to the doctor or do I really need that MRI?
So
Speaker 10: families like mine are bracing for higher premiums, deductibles, and co-pays, and then we'll be forced to ask ourselves, how sick do I have to be before I can justify paying for treatment? And that's not how health care should work in the wealthiest country in the world. And this is the moment for Congress to act. Let's protect the people of this country now. Handing it back to you, Senator Murray.
Thank
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): you. Thank you to both of you for sharing your perspective and I will turn it over Naomi to you to
call on
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): any press. Thanks
Speaker 1: everyone. We now have some time for questions from reporters in attendance. To kick things off we'll go to Orion with the Spokesman Review. Thank
you Naomi and thank
Speaker 11: you Senator for doing this to everybody on the call. Senator I
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): talked yesterday with Dan Newhouse who of course is not in you know
One
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): of the negotiators on the GOP side, but as an appropriator, he suggested that, you know, he and other Republicans would be open to some kind of middle ground on ACA subsidies, perhaps extending them, but tapering off or, or, you know, reducing eligibility for higher income earners. Is that something you and Democratic leaders are open to?
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): Look, we are open to a discussion on how to get this done so that we can get it done in time.
for
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): it to make a difference for people who are going to see these exorbitant costs. But what Republicans are saying to us so far is, just open up the government, we'll do it. And we have seen this talk for nine months now where, don't worry, we'll take care of it.
And
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): then Trump says, don't, and they don't. So we need to have them come to the table, negotiate with us, and get this done on this bill before it's too late.
Thank
Speaker 13: you. Just a quick follow
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): up. If GOP leaders stick to their current line and are not willing to negotiate, how long are you and your fellow Democratic leaders willing to hold your
line
Speaker 14: and not reopen the government?
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Well, I think the question I will put to you in reverse is how long Republicans want to hold the American people hostage because they
Speaker 15: don't want to fix a health care crisis that is in front of us today.
All
Speaker 16: right. Thank
you.
And next
Speaker 17: we'll turn to Celine, if you can say your name and out loud.
Speaker 18: Yes. Hi, my name is Celine Stevens. I'm with KJW News in Portland,
Speaker 19: Oregon. Again, thank you for taking your questions. This is a little bit more broad. Do you know how many Washingtonians would be impacted, one, by this government shutdown
Speaker 20: and then also by, as you called it, this healthcare crisis, just numbers for both of them?
Speaker 21: Well, I can't answer the first,
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): but I can tell you, and Commissioner Cooter can probably answer better than I can. Just on the ACA tax credits, I believe there's over 200,000, 220,000, Patty, that will be impacted by this.
Okay.
there we
Speaker 7: go. Yeah, we have 216,000 people. That's, that's over three quarters of the people on the exchange that get that qualify for enhanced premium tax credits that will be impacted by
this.
That's the
Speaker 22: direct impact I want to add. The fact is that if we lose that many people
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): on the health care exchanges, people still get health care and providers, hospitals, doctors are telling me these people will still show up, they will become uncompensated, which means everybody's health insurance, health care costs will go up to be able to cover those. We have seen this before when the ACA
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): When we passed it, the uninsured rate in Washington State was over 15%. When we passed the ACA, which we're talking about now, it dropped to less than 5%. So that many more
Speaker 23: people being covered meant everybody's costs went down.
Thank you. And now
Speaker 17: we'll go to Erin with BeGov.
Speaker 25: Hi. Thank you, Senator, for holding this. I was just curious, especially because both you and Senator Collins on the Appropriations
Speaker 26: Committee are known for reaching across the aisle. Have you been able to have conversations with her about the premium tax credits or kind of finding a way forward out of the shutdown? Yeah.
I
Speaker 2: think both of us have been very clear that we need a bipartisan agreement. I am talking
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): to her and I know she wants that as well, but what we need is for our leaders, for Leader Thune and Speaker Johnson to speak to our Democratic leaders. They have refused to do that for months now. We have been
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): telling them at our level we can
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): get things done, but we can't get it done if Speaker Johnson isn't going to let the appropriators move forward. And
just to follow up
Speaker 26: on that, so it sounds like you've been saying that to Republican leaders. Has Senator Collins also been carrying that message to their leadership? I would
Speaker 27: like her to answer that on her own. I don't want to answer it for her. Okay, thank you.
And now we'll go to
Speaker 28: Matthew with Washington Post. Hi,
Speaker 29 (lower-pitched voice): Senator. Thanks so much for joining us. Yes.
Speaker 29 (lower-pitched voice): Could you maybe talk about where your line is in terms of what would get you to vote to reopen the government if the Republicans were to issue some kind of verbal commitment or something like that to include extensions for the ACA subsidies? Or does it really have to be included in whatever kind of CR mechanism that ends up?
I
Speaker 29 (lower-pitched voice): can speak
Speaker 2: for me. A verbal commitment is let's just open government and we will take care of this later is not good enough for
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): me. We have been seeing this for months now. Don't worry. We're going to do this. We'll pass appropriations bills. We'll get them out of conference. We'll get them to the president. And all we've been told is next week, next week, next week.
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): it isn't completed. So it is not good enough
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): to me on the appropriation side or on the ACA side is let's just open government. We'll figure it out later. That is an empty promise
Speaker 31: that this president himself will turn on. And
we'll go over to Savannah
Speaker 32: with the National Journal.
Hi,
Speaker 33: Senator. Thank you so much for doing this.
I
Speaker 34: was just hoping to get a quick reaction to the threats coming from Russell Vogt on some of these perhaps mass layoffs that we could be seeing and perhaps some of them could be permanent. So just hoping to get your reaction to that bit of news.
You
Speaker 31: know, this is not time for kids to be fighting on a playground. Russell Vogt
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): uses taunts. So does the president. They use threats. Why do they want to hurt the American people? You would think if they wanted to do the right thing for this country, for
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): the people in this country, they would work with us to solve these problems, not threaten people. That's not how you solve anything. And that kind of level of taunting and scaring people, we just...
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): you know, keep scaring
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): people. You've been doing it for nine months. What's different? And
now we'll go to Jake with the Washington
Speaker 36: State Standard. Hey,
thanks for doing
Speaker 37: this. For Senator Murray,
Speaker 38 (lower-pitched voice): I was just wondering, separate from the subsidies, what impacts you've heard so far to the WIC program in Washington from the shutdown or nationally, more generally?
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): Well, I know the President and vote like to threaten everybody about that. The fact is that there are funds in place right now for us to currently providing WIC unless the President decides to just really be mean and shut it off. And, you know, we will work within what we have to make sure that
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): doesn't happen. But we have seen this President, we know what he does, but you don't get your way by taunting
everybody.
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): and scaring and threatening. You get your way by
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): sitting down and working with people. And frankly, that is what we've been asking the Republican leadership to do, is don't put in front of us a partisan bill that you've not even talked to us about that does nothing to address your concerns. Turn around and say, we
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): need Democrats to vote for this, but don't give us anything to vote for.
And just a
Speaker 38 (lower-pitched voice): quick follow-up, when you say funds in place, is that the contingency of $150 million? I don't
want to
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): speak to specifics on that. Let me see if I can get that to you, but I don't want to give you misinformation at this point. I
Speaker 39: appreciate it.
All
Speaker 40: right. I'm not seeing other hands raised, but I'm going to give another minute if anyone has another question
Speaker 1: they'd like to ask. You can either raise your hand or if you weren't able to do the raise hand function, you can go
ahead and unmute
Speaker 41: yourself. And we'll go back to Orion.
Thank you.
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): If you don't mind, just one more. Senator,
I wonder
If
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): you are open to separating the ACA
Speaker 42: subsidies from the Medicaid provisions from the, you know, in the GOP reconciliation bill.
Speaker 2: Yeah, I'm not going to negotiate with you at a press conference,
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): but I will tell you what needs to happen is Thune and Johnson need to turn to our Democratic leaders
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): and sit down and find out where
Speaker 43: they can find a place of agreement that assures us that they're going to take this crisis seriously.
Well, it
Speaker 44: would help me if you would negotiate with me in a press conference,
Speaker 45: but I understand. Okay, you bet. Thank you.
And we'll go
Speaker 46: to Selena Simmons-Deffen with NPR.
Hi, I have a
Speaker 47 (higher-pitched voice): question about Medicare waivers that enable hospital at home and telehealth. Since I understand they lapsed yesterday, September 30th, I'm wondering if you can speak to what
like
Speaker 47 (higher-pitched voice): how that might be playing out
Speaker 48: and how that might be affecting people now.
Well,
Speaker 21: the extension of that is included in our Democratic CR that we
Speaker 2: are offering. I believe it is in the Republican as well. So we will do everything we can to work that out.
All
Speaker 49: right. Last call
Speaker 50: for questions here. If you were not able to use the raise hand function, you can mute yourself. I'm just going to do last call.
Speaker 1: Great. Not seeing any other questions. We're going to go ahead and wrap. I'm going to turn it to Senator Murray to close us out. Thank
you
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): so much. I mean, the answer really is simple here. Republicans need to work with Democrats to solve this problem before it's too late. We do not want to shut government down. We've been offering and saying we're at the table. We're here for weeks now. We need the Republicans to come and work with us. That's what's going to solve this.